Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
Did you know that as many as
37% of breast cancer cases
may be attributable to exposure
to bovine leukemia virus?
Here’s our first story.
The incidence of breast cancer is
continuously increasing worldwide.
In the U.S., this amounted
to a 40 percent increase
in the incidence by the
turn of this century.
Currently, the main approach is
early detection and treatment.
That’s important, but why not pay
more attention to primary prevention;
in other words, protecting
people from being exposed to
risk factors for breast cancer
so that they never develop
breast cancer in the ﬁrst place.
“Overall, it is estimated that
20 percent of all human cancers
have an infectious origin.”
Viruses can trigger cancer
by turning on cancer genes
or turning off cancer
suppressing genes,
but they can also
contribute to tumor formation
just by causing chronic inflammation.
Currently, cancer-causing viruses
are considered the major
plausible hypothesis for a direct
cause of human breast cancer.
How did we get here?
It all started about 40 years ago
when a professor of virology
at UC Berkeley learned how mouse
mammary tumor virus was discovered.
Scientists swapped baby mouse pups
from mice with a high incidence
of mammary cancer with pups from
mouse strains with a low incidence
and found that the cancer
incidence matched the foster mothers,
showing it wasn’t genetic.
“It occurred to me,”
the professor thought,
“that humans are foster-
nursed on the cow.”
Bovine leukemia virus (BLV)
had just been identified as a
cancer-causing cow virus.
At the time only about 1 in 10
U.S. dairy cows were infected,
but now it’s closer to half.
We started out with
2/3s of herds affected.
Then, it was more like 80 percent,
based on their milk
testing positive for the virus, and 100
percent of the larger industrial farms.
And now, more than 9 out of 10
U.S. herds are affected,
a continuation of the
historical trend of the persistent
proliferation of BLV
within U.S. dairy herds.
We’ve long known that countries
with the highest milk consumption
also had the highest
breast cancer incidence.
And it’s not just a matchup
between dairy consumption
and breast cancer incidence
on the country level.
Individual women who are lactose
intolerant and consume less dairy
also seem to have decreased
risk of breast cancer.
Oh, but come on, there’s lots
of stuff in milk that could be
contributing to the cancer
risk like saturated fat and the
presence of cancer-promoting
growth hormones like IGF-1.
Yes, we know bovine leukemia virus
is present in marketed
beef and dairy products.
About half of milk and meat samples
turn up positive for the virus.
In fact, you can sample the virus
straight out of the air on dairy farms,
on surfaces, and in the milk itself.
Most milk is pasteurized,
but many dairy products
like raw aged cheeses are not.
And who hasn’t eaten a pink-
in-the-middle hamburger
at some point in their life?
Yes, we have evidence that
people are exposed to the virus.
Yes, we have evidence that people
are actively infected with the virus.
But it wasn’t until 2015 that we
learned infection rates were highest
in cancerous breast tissue, so much
so that as many as 37 percent
of breast cancer cases may
be attributable to exposure
to the bovine leukemia virus.
That was enough for me to
trigger a whole series of videos
on the role the virus
plays in breast cancer
and how the meat and dairy
industries responded to the news.
Okay, now that we’re all back up
to speed, what’s the latest update?
That’s what I’ll cover next.
In 2015, researchers in California
found bovine leukemia virus (BLV)
stitched into the DNA of
human breast cancer tumors from
mastectomies at such higher
rates than was found
in normal breast tissue taken
from breast reduction surgery
that they calculated that
as many as 37 percent
of breast cancer cases
may be attributable to
bovine leukemia virus exposure,
likely through the
consumption of milk or meat
obtained from infected animals.
In response, the milk and
meat industries seemed more
concerned about consumer
confidence than consumer cancer.
But scientifically, the
research priority turned to:
could the California results be replicated?
The answer, it turns out, was yes.
They were replicated among women
in Iran. Replicated in Brazil.
In Australia, the link
was even stronger.
In Texas, the same thing.
Women diagnosed with breast cancer
were found to be so much
more likely to have
bovine leukemia virus DNA
in their breast tissue
compared with women without cancer,
that the attributable risk
was calculated at 51.82 percent,
indicating that this meat
and dairy virus could be
responsible for at least one-half
of the breast cancer cases among
the women in Texas they studied.
All in all, six of the eight
studies performed to date
found the virus in human breast tissues,
which suggests strongly that
BLV does infect humans,
and breasts can be targets of infection.
Four of the five studies that were
able to compare infection rates
in cancerous tissue versus normal
breast tissue found the odds
of finding the virus in the tumors
was on average four times higher.
How does that compare to other
breast cancer risk factors?
If you go on hormone
replacement for five years,
you can bump up your breast
cancer risk 30 percent.
If you take the pill for
more than a dozen years,
your risk may go up 40 percent.
If you’re obese when you’re older,
your risk can go up 60 percent.
Having a first degree
relative with breast cancer
may double your risk,
But having your breast infected
with bovine leukemia virus
may quadruple your risk; increase
your risk hundreds of percent.
The only risk factors more
potent than BLV infection
were having the BRCA gene
mutations like Angelina Jolie has
or a high dose of ionizing radiation,
like being in the wrong place
at decidedly the wrong time.
Beyond confirmation, one study
suggested that older patients
had a greater likelihood of testing positive
for bovine leukemia virus.
That makes sense if BLV is
from exposure to dairy and meat.
The older we get, the
more meals we’ve had,
the more opportunities to
become infected over time.
Researchers also discovered
that the virus comes first,
present in some breast
tissues 3 to 10 years
before cancer was diagnosed.
“This argues against
the idea of viral invasion
of already malignant
cells,” quashing the theory
that maybe the virus is
somehow just attracted
to the cancer after the fact.
Could this explain the
consistent findings that
breast cancer tissue is more
likely to harbor infection?
Again, the data showed no;
the virus appeared to come first.
This review doesn’t provide
absolute proof that BLV
is a cause of breast cancer,
but based on the best
available balance of evidence,
BLV infection does indeed
appear to be a breast cancer risk factor.
The latest revelation is that it’s now
been found in human blood, too.
This has a number of potential ramifications.
Blood banks, for example,
don’t screen for it;
so, it’s possible you can get it
from consuming meat or dairy
or getting blood from someone
who consumed meat or dairy.
This could also mean that BLV could
cause leukemia in people, too.
It does in chimpanzees.
Two infant chimps were fed milk
from cows naturally infected
with the BLV, and they
both died of leukemia.
We didn’t even know
chimps could get leukemia.
This certainly suggests the
possibility of transmission or
induction of leukemia through
the ingestion of milk from
BLV-infected cows; or blood-
borne spread could carry
the virus to other organs.
In cattle, the virus
causes blood cancers,
but this may just be because
dairy cattle are turned into
hamburger when they are
still so young, so maybe
they don’t have time for
tumors to grow in other organs.
How concerned should we be
about bovine leukemia virus?
It is not clear yet whether
this is a good news story
or a bad news story.
If subsequent studies show that
BLV does cause breast cancer
in humans, this will have
significant repercussions
for the dairy and cattle industries.
But that means there is
something we can do about it.
Perhaps attempts should be made
to eradicate the infection
from cattle now, rather than
wait for the final word.
Twenty-one nations have eradicated
BLV from their dairy cattle.
In contrast, in the U.S. the BLV
prevalence just keeps going up.
If the industries are not going
to step up and try to eliminate
the disease, then the least
they could do is eliminate
some of the practices that spread
the disease between animals.
BLV is spread via blood through
contaminated needles,
saw or gouge dehorners, tattoo pliers,
ear taggers, hoof knives,
nose tongs, and other tools
of the agribusiness trade.
Though in view of the
emerging information about BLV
in human breast cancer, it
may be prudent to encourage
the complete elimination of BLV in cattle,
particularly in the dairy industry.
The hope is that either
way it may help reduce
the scourge of breast cancer.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.